בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is קמ"ח, Kuf-Mem-Ches, 148. We're
dealing with, we're getting into the meat of the idea of a
מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv mei-ra, and we had two opinions whether
it was דאורייתא de-oraisa or דרבנן. de-rabbanan. And one of the questions
that the גמרא, Gemara, and תוספות Tosafos says דאורייתא de-oraisa doesn't exactly
mean דאורייתא, de-oraisa, but it sounds like it does from the גמרא.
Gemara. And within the דרבנן de-rabbanan question, the גמרא's Gemara question is,
well if that's true, how does that fit with שמואל's Shmuel idea
that if you sell a שטר חוב, shtar chov, the original creditor
can annul it, it's clear, but if he gave it by a
מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv mei-ra, he can't. And the גמרא Gemara
says that sounds like it's דאורייתא. de-oraisa. Now what that has to
do with דאורייתא de-oraisa is not clear. It could just mean that
if it has that weight, then the מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv
mei-ra, which is, you know, then how could if it, I'm sorry.
Yes, that sounds like a דאורייתא. de-oraisa. It could be that it's
דרבנן, de-rabbanan, how could a rabbinic institution like transferring a debt, how
could that win out against the ability to be מוחל mochel the
debt? The better explanation, I think, which I offered, which of course
isn't my own, is that if it's rabbinic, then it should be
working along the same models and mechanisms as normal transfer and sale.
So the same way in normal transfer and sale the original creditor
can annul a debt, so by מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv mei-ra
the original creditor can annul a debt. But if it's דאורייתא, de-oraisa,
it's based on the model of ירושה, yerusha, of inheritance. So if
the one who receives the debt is like the child who inherited,
you know, the money owed to their father, you know, the debt
from the creditor's side, so then you can't annul it because now
it's like the heir to this, you know, to the debt. So
the argument of דאורייתא de-oraisa is really an argument that it works
on the model of ירושה. yerusha. And then it would explain why
if somebody is given a debt, you know, there's got to be
a better word than this. Anyway, is given the anyway the, you
know, IOU, he's given it through, you know, through a מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnas shchiv mei-ra, why it can no longer be annulled because
he becomes like the heir. So anyway, that should indicate that it's
a דאורייתא. de-oraisa. So the גמרא Gemara says no, it's דרבנן de-rabbanan
that they made it like a דאורייתא. de-oraisa. So again, given the
two explanations we had, that either means they gave it the same
weight as a דאורייתא, de-oraisa, or given what I just said, it
means that it's a דרבנן de-rabbanan but we're still modeling it more
after ירושה, yerusha, more after inheritance, and after a קנין, kinyan, a
normal type of a transaction. And we're going to see exactly that
now as we continue. So let's continue to again the דף daf
is קמ"ח, Kuf-Mem-Ches, 148, I don't know if I said that. And
we take let's continue קמ"ז עמוד ב', Kuf-Mem-Zayin amud bais, the following.
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, 1, 2, 3, seven lines from
the bottom. Lines start with Rav Nachman. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman, or אמר, amar, שכיב מרע שאמר shchiv mei-ra she-amar ידור פלוני
בבית זה. yeidor ploni bevayis zeh. So שכיב מרע shchiv mei-ra says
on his deathbed, let Reuven, you know, be able to live in
this house. Okay, now that sounds like a normal thing that we
would imagine somebody would sort of say on his deathbed. You know,
we discussed the other day that the גמרא Gemara sort of mentioned,
alluded to this idea of the ethical will, right? Somebody sort of
passing over their life lessons, you know, in you know before they
die. But there's but the classic I would say thing about like
צו לביתך, tzava levosecha, which is the פסוק pasuk that the גמרא
Gemara quoted the other day, is neither the life lessons, nor is
it the, you know, distribution of property. It's more sort of like
give instructions, you know, what you want done, right? How you want
these accounts handled and how you want this done and so on.
So it's neither again a transferring of property, it's not some ethical
will, it's like directions in terms of what to, you know, be
doing in the home and with and so on. So like, you
know, always make sure the kids get together for חנוכה, Chanukah, you
know, those types of things, right? So they're not exactly they're neither
one nor the other. So here's what this sounds like. The guy's
dying, he's not transferring ownership of the house to Reuven, but he
says Reuven should always be able to live in this house. Okay,
ידור פלוני בבית זה, yeidor ploni bevayis zeh, that Reuven live in
this house.
יאכל פלוני פירות דקל זה. yochal ploni peiros de-ikal zeh. Always give
Reuven the apples from that apple tree over there. Okay, so that's
not a that's not something that exists yet. The living in the
house is an abstraction, whatever, apples haven't you know don't exist yet
in the world. So it doesn't really so the הלכה halacha is
לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, that was nothing. I mean, you
know, if the family and the kids want to do what Dad
wanted, you know, then maybe they'll do it to fulfill Dad's wishes.
But it's not a gift of a שכיב מרע. shchiv mei-ra. There's
no property that is being transferred. אם כן, Im kein, Rav says,
עד שיאמר, ad she-yomar, what he has to say is, תנו בית
זה לפלוני, tenu bayis zeh le-ploni, give Reuven this house, וידור בו,
ve-yeidor bo, and let him live in it.
תנו דקל זה לפלוני tenu de-ikal zeh le-ploni ויאכל פירותיו. ve-yochal peirosav.
Of course you don't have to
say וידור בו ve-yeidor bo or ויאכל פירותיו, ve-yochal peirosav, once you're
giving it to him obviously he can do it. But it means
if you want him to live in it, you have to give
him the house. You want him to have the to get the
fruit, you give him the tree. Now there's also a way you
can sort of do something in the middle, you can say הקנה
את האילן לפירותיו, hikneh et ha-ilan l'peirosav, you know, one of those
types of like partial קניינים, kinyanim, you own it for this purpose,
but nevertheless, there has to actually be a there has to actually
be a... property transfer. Anything else is not legally binding. But if
you create a type of תנאי, tnai, in
other words, let's say he moves into the house and so he
says, give him the house so he can live in it. So
he goes into the house and he sells the house. Oh, that's
an interesting question.
That's an interesting question.
Same thing with the דקל. dekel.
Yeah, that's an interesting question, meaning, I don't know, that's a really
good question and I don't know the answer to that, which is,
I mean obviously in a normal קנין kinyan you could do that.
I mean you could certainly say he can own the house לצורך
דירה, letzorech dira, you know, but by a תנאי, tnai, you know,
I maybe it has to do with which model the מתנת שכיב
מרע matnat shchiv mera works on. Like a קנין kinyan model or
a ירושה yerusha model? Because can you give a מתנת שכיב מרע
matnat shchiv mera בתנאי? bitnai? Because I'm thinking...
No, I understand.
I'm just saying as a general question. I understand your point. Yeah,
I want him to have it because I want him to be
able to have a place to live, not because I want him
to make a profit off of it. I get it. Right, but
my question... I totally understand the scenario. My question is in general,
like not a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera for this purpose,
like a limited קנין, kinyan, right? But to actually sort of say,
and if this condition isn't satisfied then I never gave it to
him in the first place. Right. So that's an interesting question, which
might have to do with whether it's the קנין kinyan model or
the ירושה yerusha model, because you can't have a ירושה yerusha בתנאי,
bitnai, you know? So that's an interesting question. Yeah, totally. So this
language is, this specific language
is not the kind of thing an unlearned person would easily get.
Right. So that's a good question in general, you know? I mean,
I guess what your point is is that like, okay, if you're
doing business transactions, you get the advice of a lawyer. So if
you're on your deathbed, who's advising you? I mean, you know, when
you write up a will you're supposed to get the advice of
a lawyer, but again your point is that if this is limited
to the time that a person's on their deathbed, right, it is
very funny to think... yeah, it's a good question. I don't know,
you're right, that's an interesting question. Like, you know, if you limit
this to the time that a person's on their deathbed, right, then
how do you then, you know, you can't always expect that everybody
knows the הלכה halacha and knows exactly how to frame their words.
That's a good point. Okay, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, okay. תנו דקלו
לפלוני ואוכל פירותיו. tinu diklo liploni ve'ochel peirotav. למימרא? lemeimra?
So the גמרא Gemara says, now what the גמרא Gemara is going
to learn out of this is the following: דסבר רב נחמן, disvar
Rav Nachman, that רב נחמן Rav Nachman holds, מילתא דאיתא בבריא איתא
בשכיב מרע. milta de'ita bevari ita bishchiv mera. Right? Something that works
with a בריא, bari, like transferring ownership of the house, works by
a שכיב מרע. shchiv mera. מילתא דליתא בבריא, milta deleita bevari, that
doesn't work by a בריא, bari, I can't give you fruit that
doesn't exist yet, I can't give you the dwelling of the house,
it's like a דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba le'olam, and
the dwelling of a house is like an abstract entity to begin
with. Okay, ליתא בשכיב מרע, leita bishchiv mera, it can't be granted
with a שכיב מרע. shchiv mera. Okay,
now is that really true? Right? This becomes interesting, because although here
שכיב מרע ככתובה וכמסורה דמי, shchiv mera kechtuva uchemsura dami, you don't
need an act of קנין, kinyan, but the question is, are there
so... okay, but does that make it like the Superman of קניינים?
kinyanim? Like it works on a whole wide range of things or
does it just mean you don't need the act of קנין? kinyan?
So here's an interesting question. Like this seems to say no, otherwise
for all other purposes besides that you don't need an act, the
words are the act. Fine, but nothing else are we saying is
a new הלכה. halacha. Everything else is like normal קניינים, kinyanim, just
that the words here create the act. All right, so then it
shouldn't work on objects that you can't do as a בריא. bari.
That seems to be consistent with this opinion. Okay, that seems to
be what this opinion is saying, which is totally reasonable. But does
this, is this true? והאמר רבא אמר רב נחמן, veha'amar Rava amar
Rav Nachman, רבא Rava says in the name of רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, דף קמ"ח, daf kuf mem chet, שכיב מרע שאמר תנו הלואתי
לפלוני הלואתו לפלוני. shchiv mera she'amar tnu halva'ati liploni halva'ato liploni. Now
this is very similar to the selling of the שטר חוב. shtar
chov. If a שכיב מרע shchiv mera says, ראובן Reuven owes me
a hundred dollars, give that debt to שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so he's
not even doing it through, give the שטר חוב shtar chov to
שמעון. Shimon. There at least, give the שטר חוב, shtar chov, a
שטר חוב shtar chov is a type of a way that normally
you transfer a debt by transferring the bill,
the writ. Okay, and the חידוש chidush was that there can't be
מחילה, mechila, and even that was just שכיב מרע shchiv mera הלכה.
halacha. Okay, but here it's a much bigger חידוש. chidush. Here there's
no way you can transfer a debt as a בריא. bari. It's
an abstract entity. All right? You need either the physical concrete שטר,
shtar, which to some degree represents the debt, to be the thing
that's transferred, and even then it's not just the piece of paper,
it has to be a special way of doing it that makes
it be the, you know, physical representation of the debt. But without
a שטר shtar you can't transfer a debt. So and nevertheless, it
says here that it works by a שכיב מרע. shchiv mera. So
it seems that a שכיב מרע shchiv mera works more powerfully than
normal קניינים. kinyanim. Okay? So and it works even on objects like
this abstract debt that a קנין kinyan doesn't work on. So if
it can work on transferring a debt, let it work on giving
a house that doesn't exist yet, or the dwelling in a house.
דאף על גב דליתא בבריא, de'af al gav deleita bevari, even though
it doesn't exist by בריא. bari. ורב פפא veRav Pappa has a
great answer. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, רב
פפא אמר הואיל ויורש Rav Pappa amar ho'il veyoresh יורשה *yorsha*, since
an heir inherits a debt, somebody who receives this by a מתנת
שכיב מרע matnat sh'chiv mera. *matnas shachiv mera* also gets it, which
again means we're building it on the model of ירושה *yerusha*, not
on the model of קניינים *kinyanim*. So the same way when somebody
dies, money owed to the father is owed to the sons, even
if there's no שטר *shtar*, even if it's just this abstract entity,
it passes on to the sons. So when a שכיב מרע shachiv
mera *shachiv mera* identifies Reuven will get it, he's basically saying Reuven
is my heir as far as this debt is concerned. And if
Reuven is my heir as far as this debt is concerned, then
now the money is owed to Reuven. So actually that works. But
you know what doesn't work? פירות pirot דקל זה *peiros dekel zeh*.
Okay, פירות peirot דקל זה *peiros dekel zeh* is still something that
the only way an heir gets the פירות דקל *peiros dekel* is
by getting the דקל *dekel*. The only way the heir gets the
right to live in the house is by getting the house. So
it's still—we're still going to exclude the פירות דקל זה *peiros dekel
zeh*. That won't work. A שכיב מרע shachiv mera? *shachiv mera* doesn't
work on everything, but it does work on the loan, because it's
building on the model of ירושה *yerusha*, not on the model of
קניינים *kinyanim*, okay? Which again, very much fits in what we said
yesterday about a שטר חוב *shtar chov*. Why you can't be מוחל
*mochel* a שטר חוב *shtar chov*? If it's built on the model
of ירושה *yerusha*, then this guy is the guy to whom the
money is owed directly. Okay, is that clear to everybody? So Rav
Papa's answer is it's built on the model of ירושה *yerusha*. It
explains why a debt transfer can be transferred. It explains why yesterday's
point of a שטר חוב *shtar chov*, it can't be, you can't
get a מחילה *mechila* after it was transferred by מתנת שכיב מרע
matnat sh'chiv mera *matnas shachiv mera*. But it would still not allow
for the fruit that does not yet exist. Okay, it allows for
certain things, particularly now two things about the loan. Okay, but it
still is not, does not allow, you know, it isn't a silver
bullet. Okay, it's still not going to, you know, it only works,
you know, to the power that ירושה *yerusha* would work. You can't
be יורש *yoresh* just fruit of a tree that doesn't yet exist.
You have to be יורש *yoresh* the tree. Yes?
Is this a—is this a good comparison? What about the מזונות *mezonos*
that are coming to a woman from the כתובה *kesuvah*? In other
words, they don't exist yet, right?
What about the מזונות *mezonos*?
In other words, that's something that she—yeah,
so she just has a—it's a debt. It's a debt owed to
her, what we said yesterday.
It's like this מלווה *milveh*. Yeah, but it's
a—it's another form of debt. It can be this point.
Yeah, but she doesn't own the fruit. She just is owed money.
So it would be like a debt. Right, exactly. Okay. Alright, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. I don't know if this was
on before or not. Yeah, memory full. Okay. But I guess that's
that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Where are we?
Okay.
Alright, so that's one answer. Rav Papa's answer is a great answer.
I love it. It's the ירושה *yerusha* answer. Let's see what the
next answer is. ורב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר *Ve'Rav Acha brei
de'Rav Ika amar*, Rav Acha the son of Rav Ika says, חובא
איתיה בברי *hova isay be'bari*. It's not true that you can't transfer
a debt with a normal healthy person, even without a שטר חוב
*shtar chov*, וכדרב הונא אמר רב דאמר רב הונא אמר רב *u'che'de'Rav
Huna amar Rav de'amar Rav Huna amar Rav*, like Rav Huna said
in the name of Rav, for Rav Huna said in the name
of Rav, מנה לי בידך *maneh li be'yadcha*, Charlie, you owe me
a hundred—you a hundred—a hundred dollars. תנהו לפלוני
*tenayhu l'ploni*, give it to a Gloria. Okay, so—I don't know Gloria
anything, but it's her birthday. I thought it was her birthday last
week. We did the same thing last week. It turns out it's
her birthday this week. Okay, so I say, Charlie, that hundred dollars
that you owe me, מנה לי בידך תנהו לפלוני *maneh li be'yadcha
tenayhu l'ploni*, במעמד שלשתן *be'ma'amad sheloshtan*, for all three in the room
at the same time, קנה *kanah*. Then—now Gloria is owed the money,
and I'm not owed the money anymore. So okay, that's true. That's
also a rabbinic model, but fine, we're working in the world of
the rabbinic—of rabbinic things, and the rabbis did allow under certain circumstances
to transfer directly the debt. And now Charlie owes the money directly
to Gloria. So if they allowed a model with a certain type
of a special קנין kinyan? *kinyan* called מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shelashtan *ma'amad
sheloshtan* where all three are in the same room, they'll allow it
with מתנת שכיב מרע matnat sh'chiv mera? *matnas shachiv mera*. The basic
חידוש *chiddush* of מתנת שכיב מרע matnat sh'chiv mera, *matnas shachiv mera*
is you don't need a מעשה קנין kinyan *ma'aseh kinyan*. Okay, so
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is here, fine, you don't
need a מעשה קנין kinyan, *ma'aseh kinyan*, but it'll work as powerfully
as a wide range of מעשי קניינים *ma'asei kinyanim*. So it'll work
just like מעמד ma'amad שלשתן *ma'amad sheloshtan* works. If by מעמד שלשתן
*ma'amad sheloshtan* you can transfer a debt, by מתנת שכיב מרע matnat
sh'chiv mera *matnas shachiv mera* you can transfer a debt. Okay, so
now we are maintaining both models remain viable models for what מתנת
שכיב מרע matnat sh'chiv mera. *matnas shachiv mera* is. Is it a
gift, מתנת *matnas*, or is it like שכיב מרע shachiv mera *shachiv
mera*, or is it like a ירושה *yerusha*, you know? Does it
work as a קנין kinyan, *kinyan* or does it work as a
ירושה *yerusha*? It doesn't work on everything. You can't transfer fruit of
a tree because fruit of a tree can't be transferred as an
abstraction separate from the tree, either through a קנין kinyan *kinyan* or
through a ירושה *yerusha*. So it does have its limits, okay? It
only works on concrete things, דבר שלא בא לעולם davar she-lo ba
la-olam *davar shelo ba l'olam*, exactly. But you can transfer debts because
there's a type of a קנין kinyan. *kinyan* that works to transfer
debts and ירושה *yerusha* transfers debts. And it might be that there
can't be מחילה *mechila* because especially if it's based on ירושה *yerusha*
model. Okay, so you have these two models, but it's not that
it works on everything. Yes?
Okay, so I have two questions. One is, is—is a debt abstract
in the same way as a דבר שלא בא לעולם davar she-lo
ba la-olam *davar shelo ba l'olam* is abstract?
Not exactly, right? No, a debt is abstract because it's not a—
Okay, so I have two questions. One is, is it debt abstract
in the same way as a דבר שלא בא לעולם davar she-lo
ba la-olam is abstract? Not exactly, right? No, debt is abstract because
it's not a concrete object, but דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo
ba l'olam, is money owed right now, right? Okay.
And why is מעמד שלשתן like what's the, what's the?
Yeah, we mentioned that before. There's different reasons. I don't want to
I don't want to get into it.
Okay, so is there a parallel between the fruit not existing yet
and the requirement of having all the parties present and if one
person's not there then it's like the מעמד's not there?
Yeah, well that's right, but the fruit's not there even with all
the parties present. A debt
might not be concrete but it exists. Okay, so that's the difference.
The fruit is
not that it's not concrete, it will be concrete when it exists
but just doesn't exist yet. You're almost like different sides of the
same coin. Okay, the fruit is concrete but it doesn't exist now.
The debt exists now but it's not concrete. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so let's take a look. גמרא Gemara says
like this. איבעיא להו, iba'aya lehu, they asked the following question: דקלא
לאחד ופירותיו לאחר מהו? dikla le-echad u-firotav le-acher mahu? Now, I'm not
going to read this the רשב"ם's Rashbam way, it's very, very confusing.
I'm going to read it תוספות's Tosafot way. Okay, just as an
alert because people in the past have corrected me because their English
says different than I'm saying. I am reading this תוספות's Tosafot way.
Alert. Okay, here's the way תוספות Tosafot is much simpler. Here's the
way תוספות Tosafot reads it. We just said that you have to
actually transfer something concrete. Let's say the שכיב מרע shachiv mera says
that, okay, I am giving the דקלא dikla to Eli and the
fruit of it to Charlie over there. Now, did Charlie get the
fruit with a שכיב מרע? shachiv mera It should seem no, we
just said right now that he can't give fruit of a tree
that doesn't exist yet. Ah, but maybe yes. Maybe when I meant
said the fruit to Charlie what I really meant was those places
on the branches that the fruit is going to come from. That's
I'm giving that to Charlie so he actually is then going to
get the fruit that emerges from it. Okay, so now why exactly
we should say that now
because before remember what he said was
יאכל פלוני פירות דקלא, yochal ploni pirot dikla, but I said Charlie
eat the fruit of the tree so clearly you're not giving him
anything concrete right now. But here I'm saying here the שכיב מרע
shachiv mera saying the tree goes to Eli and the fruit of
it to Charlie. So maybe there you mean you own Charlie will
own a piece of the tree from which the fruit will come
and therefore it will actually be something concrete.
Okay. דקלא לאחד ופירותיו לאחר מהו? dikla le-echad u-firotav le-acher mahu? What's
the הלכה? halacha? שייר מקום פירות או לא שייר? shiyer mekom pirot
o lo shiyer? Does the שכיב מרע shachiv mera leave over the
place of the fruit so that when it's being given to the
person he's not just getting the future fruit, he's actually getting the
place of the fruit on the tree? Okay, I don't even know
why the גמרא Gemara doesn't do another split because it's classic split
which is let Charlie own the דקלא לפירותיו. dikla le-firotav. You own
the whole tree for the purpose of its fruit,
but which would seem the classic way in which you transfer just
the fruit and not the title. But anyway, this is the way
the גמרא Gemara is understanding.
Why do you need two people in this case? דקלא dikla to
one person and the פירות to somebody else.
You could just say let someone because before we had the example
let someone eat the fruit. We're going to get to one person
in a minute. Okay, well actually in the reverse, but let's take
a look. Okay, but it could just be that since you're transferring
ownership to one it should be assumed that you're transferring ownership to
the other. If somebody just says Charlie should have the fruit of
the tree then that just means a דבר שלא בא לעולם and
it doesn't work. But if somebody says Eli have the tree and
Charlie have the fruit, since by Eli we're talking about a קניין
kinyan in the tree, maybe we're talking about a קניין kinyan in
the tree for Charlie as well.
Okay, so שייר מקום פירות או לא שייר? shiyer mekom pirot o
lo shiyer? אם תמצי לומר לאחר לא הוי שיור. im timtzi lomar
le-acher lo havei shiyur. No, when it's dealing with somebody other than
the שכיב מרע shachiv mera himself, he's not actually leaving over a
piece in the tree. Charlie is just getting the fruit, not a
part of the tree for the fruit, which means it's דבר שלא
בא לעולם and sorry Charlie you're out, you don't get anything.
Okay, but לעצמו חוץ מפירותיו מהו? le-atzmo chutz mi-pirotav mahu? Let's say
the שכיב מרע shechiv meira says I want to give Eli the
tree and the שכיב מרע shechiv meira, wants to keep for himself
and he says and I get to keep the fruit.
Okay, so maybe self-interest is when you're talking about yourself you're always
keeping a little bit extra. You've got your own interest way more
heavily than somebody else's interest, although at the time of death you
would think not so much, but okay. Anyway, so in that case
when he's keeping it for himself maybe he's actually keeping the
actual a part of the tree for its fruit. Because if the
שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera said I'm giving my entire tree to ראובן
Reuven there but I still get to eat the fruit of it,
first of all it's funny he's going to be dead when it
takes effect, but I don't know my kids still get to eat
the fruit of it.
So in that case if that was just the abstraction, let's say
he said not get to eat, let's say he said the entire
tree is transferred to ראובן Reuven but all its future fruit remain
in the possession of my kids. Okay. You can't do that, because
if you're transferring the entire title to Reuven, how are you managing
to keep the future fruit to yourself? So even though it's אין
אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, ein adam makneh davar shelo ba
l'olam, you can't sell future fruit, it doesn't exist, and here it's
a little different, here it's retaining future fruit. It's still the same
idea. If you transfer the entire title without retaining some ownership in
the tree itself, how do you manage to hold on to the
future fruit? So the only way it would work is if when
he says and I get to keep the fruit of the fruit,
he meant I get to keep a part of the tree that
will, you know, for the purpose of the fruit. Otherwise you can't
keep the fruit if you've totally transferred the ownership of the tree.
Okay, if he wanted to give him the tree and he wanted
to retain ownership of the fruit, could the person who got the
tree chop the tree down?
Well, it would depend how he splits it, but possibly. The best
way to do this, the classic way the Gemara says is his
גוף guf to Reuven, I'm going to retain דקל לפירותיו dekel l'peirotav
and I'm going to transfer the גוף guf of it to somebody
else. Okay, and then yes, the other person who has the title
might be able to chop it down.
If you say why is he buying the tree?
Right, if they can't get the fruit. Exactly, exactly.
Okay, so now the Gemara says אם תמצא לומר דקל לאחד ופירותיו
לעצמו חוץ מפירותיו מהו.
Im timtza lomar dekel l'echad u'peirotav l'atzmo
chutz mipeirotav mahu. אמר רב עמרם אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Amram
amar Rav Nachman, אם תמצא לומר im timtza lomar it's going to
be a little wordy now. אם תמצא לומר דקל לאחד ופירותיו לאחר
לא השאיר Im timtza lomar dekel l'echad u'peirotav l'acher lo hashayir when
you split it, so the guy who you're giving the fruit to,
we're saying you just gave him the fruit, not a part of
the tree, and he gets nothing. Okay, מקום פרי דקל לאחד. makom
peiri dekel l'echad. לא השאיר מקום פרי דקל. Lo hashayir makom peiri
dekel. מקום פרי דקל, makom peiri dekel, excuse me.
You were not leaving over the place of the fruit, you know,
a piece of the tree right where the fruit will grow from,
you're not leaving that to the other guy and you're just trying
to give the fruit to the other guy and therefore he gets
nothing. But מקום פרי, makom peiri, let's try it one more time.
אמר רב עמרם אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Amram amar Rav Nachman,
אם תמצא לומר דקל לאחד ופירותיו לאחר לא השאיר מקום פרי. im
timtza lomar dekel l'echad u'peirotav l'acher lo hashayir makom peiri. Okay,
if you're going to say in that case you're not leaving over
to the other guy the place of the fruit, you're just giving
him the fruit and therefore he gets nothing, דקל לאחד ושייר פירותיו
לפניו dekel l'echad v'shayir peirotav l'fanav
if the guy is trying to give the tree to somebody and
keep the fruit for himself, שייר מקום פרי. shayer makom peiri. Yes,
in that case we're going to assume that you're actually holding on
to some ownership of the tree and actually it is good what
you're holding on for yourself. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama what's the reason?
כל לגבי נפשיה בעין יפה משייר. Kol l'gabei nafshih b'ayin yafa meshayer.
Remember the עין יפה, ayin yafa, עין רע? ayin ra? Anytime it's
your own interests, you're going to be a little bit more generous
towards yourself. Okay, of course how does that fit in with general
עין רע, ayin ra, עין יפה, ayin yafa, I don't know. It's
a larger question.
Anytime you say מקום פרי makom peiri you're only doubtful about what
you say for yourself.
No, you don't say מקום פרי. makom peiri. If you say מקום
פרי, makom peiri, if the שכיב מרע Shchiv meira said you know
the tree to Reuven and מקום פרי makom peiri to Charlie, it
would work,
because you're actually leaving over the מקום פרי. makom peiri. If you
don't know it, you're just saying פרי peiri and are we going
to translate it and interpret it to mean מקום פרי. makom peiri.
So when it's to people, no, because okay, so Charlie doesn't get,
Charlie doesn't get, but I was only trying to give him the
fruit. But when it's to myself, then we say when I say
when the guy says I'm keeping the fruit, he means I'm keeping
the מקום פרי. makom peiri. Okay, we interpret it to mean more.
You could also say it's not just a question of what he
means and what his intent is, but it's almost like a question
of like inertia. Since he owns the entire tree, it needs a
higher threshold to get it all fully out of his control, right?
So it could also have been that that's like a different, slightly
different mechanism. Yes.
If you sell me the tree and you sell the fruit or
the branches that have the fruit to someone else, I should be
able to chop down the tree.
Yeah, that's what they would ask. And you could, you might very
well be able to do that. Okay, fine, but we can also
come to an agreement. Okay, fine. אמר ליה רב אבא לרב אשי,
Amar lei Rav Abba l'Rav Ashi, Rav Abba says to Rav Ashi,
אנן אדריש לקיש מתנינן לה. Anan ad'Reish Lakish matninan lah.
This difference between like the מקום פרי makom peiri and the פרי
peiri itself or whatever, we talk that not about this case of
like the שכיב מרע, shchiv meira but we talk about it in
another case on the teaching of
ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, המוכר בית
לחבירו ואמר לו על מנת שדיוטא עליונה שלי, hamocher bayit l'chavero v'amar
lo al menat she'diyuta eliyona sheli, I'm selling you this house but
I'm keeping the upper
story, דיוטא עליונה שלו, diyuta eliyona shelo, he keeps the upper story.
That's how they said it. Okay, moving on. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu,
now they raise the following
question: בית לאחד ודיוטא לאחר. Bayit l'echad v'diyuta l'acher. Okay, or לאחר,
l'acher, I can't even read it. So, the guy says now I'm
selling my house to Eli and the second story to Charlie. מהו?
Mahu? What do we say? Now what's the question? It's very clear,
everything is very concrete, it's not like fruit, what's the issue? Here's
the issue: מי השאיר או לא, Mi hashayir o lo, am I
leaving something over? What am I leaving over? So what we're about
to see is going way back to early בבא בתרא Bava Batra
topics, when I say I'm selling you know am I giving Charlie
not just the second story but the room to like put things
outside of his window?
extend some beam or whatever outside of his window. So that's a
שיור *shiyur*, okay? Which is very funny, like where do you get
that in the language? But let's take a look. אם תמצי לומר
ביתא לחד ודיוטא לחד לא הוי שיור *Im timtza lomar beita le-khad
ve-dyuta le-khad lo havei shiyur*. I'm not leaving Charlie that light, I'm
just giving him the second story. Why should it be that I'm
giving him some air rights in the yard? But
חוץ מדיוטא *khutz mi-dyuta* מהו *mahu*? If you sell it to somebody
and retain, say, and I'm keeping the second story, maybe for yourself
you are going to retain the air rights. Now again, it could
just be this general idea that you keep more for yourself. But
also what the Rashbam points out is that when you're selling to
somebody else the house, you didn't have to say 'except for the
second story.' Except
for us maybe you obviously did,
but
for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the default is that the מוכר את
הבית לא מוכר את העליה *mokher es ha-bayis lo mokher es ha-aliya*,
you might remember going back a lot of פרקים *prakim*, okay? So
automatically if you just say I'm just selling the house, it doesn't
include the second story. Why did you say explicitly 'but except for
the second story'? Maybe that extra language was to retain even more
rights for yourself. Okay? And that's so it's even a different logic
here. It's not just because you favor yourself over other people.
But isn't this the second story that they built with flat roofs?
Like if the family expanded, they would, it was like another house.
Right, exactly. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says חוץ מדיוטא *khutz
mi-dyuta* מהו *mahu*? אמר רבא אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rava amar Rav
Nachman* said on this case, אם תמצי לומר ביתא לחד ודיוטא לחד
לא הוי שיור *Im timtza lomar beita le-khad ve-dyuta le-khad lo havei
shiyur*. Okay, if you're just selling the bottom floor to one and
the top floor to the other, you're not leaving over any extra
air rights. But חוץ מדיוטא הוי שיור *khutz mi-dyuta havei shiyur*. If
you say for yourself except for the second story, you are leaving
yourself extra air rights. Okay, ואליבא דרב זביד *ve-aliba d'Rav Zavid*, and
here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* spells out that we mean air rights,
דאמר *d'amar*, who says, שאם רצה להוציא בזיזין מוציא *she-im ratza lehotzi
be-zizin motzi*. You can put protrusions coming out of the wall. עלמא
*alma*, so you see, כיון דשייר דיוטא מקום זיזין נמי שייר *keivan
de-shiyer dyuta makom zizin nami shiyer*. If you're explicitly for yourself, not
to somebody else, leaving over the second story, you're also leaving over
your right to bring out these protrusions. And now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* somehow had this גרסא *girsa* to tie back to the earlier
discussion, הכא נמי *hacha nami* כיון דאמר חוץ מפירותיה מקום פירות שייר
*keivan de-amar khutz mi-peroseha makom peirot shiyer*. So maybe we could then
make the analogy, meaning without that parenthesis, it's just saying this was
a completely different discussion. Here it's saying even if it was a
different discussion, we can make an analogy and say that therefore when
a person sells a tree and leaves the fruit for themselves, they're
actually leaving the fruit for themselves with some extra right, with I
mean not extra rights, but like with ownership of the tree to
keep the fruit. Of course, completely not a good comparison, right? Because
in one case you didn't have to say חוץ מדיוטא *khutz mi-dyuta*,
it was an extra language, but anyway, that's why you might want
to take out those parentheses because it's not a good analogy. Anyway,
that basic פשט *pshat* of all of that was that even when
a שכיב מרע shchiv mera *shkhiv mera* transfers something, and even if
he has the ability to transfer things a ברי *bari* can't transfer
like a debt, okay, that's limited. The basic rule is that you
have to be you can't do more than a ברי *bari* can
do, and therefore a שכיב מרע shchiv mera, *shkhiv mera* cannot transfer
just the fruit of the tree without actually transferring ownership of the
tree. But if he tries to retain the fruit of the tree,
we're going to interpret that to be retaining a certain ownership of
the tree itself in order to allow that to work. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
Now we get back to
more like some basic new parameters around a שכיב מרע *shkhiv mera*.
Okay, so one parameter was concrete, not דבר שלא בא לעולם *davar
she-lo ba le-olam*, but it can be a debt. Debt yes, דבר
שלא בא לעולם *davar she-lo ba le-olam* no. Okay, and now we're
going to get on to some the basic issues about כל נכסיו
kol nechasav. *kol nekhasav* versus מקצת נכסיו miktzat nechasav. *miktzas nekhasav*.
Yes. It's interesting, the air, meaning the air rights, the space is
analogous to the branch where something else can be put there,
it's a strange comparison.
Yeah, it is very strange.
Well, which is why the air is compared to the branch.
Right, which is why you'd take out the parentheses, we're not even
making the comparison, we're just saying it was a different discussion. אמר
רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi
amar Rav Nachman *Amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman*, שכיב
מרע שכתב כל נכסיו לאחרים sh'chiv mera shekatav kol nechasav l'acherim. *shkhiv
mera she-kasav kol nekhasav le-akheirim*. So now remember, here's the general rule:
This is the הלכה halacha *halakha* of the שכיב מרע *shkhiv mera*
כל נכסיו kol nechasav. *kol nekhasav*. And the and the basic חידוש
*khiddush* of a שכיב מרע *shkhiv mera* are these two things: a
קנין kinyan. *kinyan* is unnecessary, the words work, and עמד חוזר amad
chozer. *amad khozer*, it's only given on the assumption of death. Anytime
it's only מקצת miktzat נכסיו nechasav *miktzas nekhasav*, it's really not a
שכיב מרע *shkhiv mera* הלכה halacha *halakha*. The guy might be in
his deathbed, but doesn't matter, it's not this new thing. So it's
a normal קנין kinyan, *kinyan*, so you need a קנין kinyan. *kinyan*.
And if it's a normal קנין kinyan *kinyan*, if he gets better,
it doesn't matter, you did a קנין kinyan. *kinyan* to somebody. Okay?
So the big question is going to be what in the line
between
כל נכסיו kol nechasav *kol nekhasav* and מקצת miktzat, נכסיו *miktzas nekhasav*.
Okay, so that's going to be asked in different ways. The משנה
Mishna, *Mishnah* says קרקע karka, כל שהוא *karka kol shehu*. So does
it have to be קרקע *karka*? Let's say the guy gave over
all of his stuff except for ten dollars. Is that כל נכסיו
kol nechasav. from the משנה, it sounds like it is כל נכסיו.
kol nechasav. It needs to be קרקע, but maybe not. Okay, we're
going to see now exactly because this makes all the difference for
both of these הלכות. halachos. So let's take a look. Okay, so
אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן שכיב מרע שכתב כל
נכסיו kol nechasav, לאחרים. Now, he gave over all of his property
to other people. Okay, ראובן Reuven gets this and שמעון Shimon gets
that and לוי Levi gets this and יהודה Yehuda gets that. Now,
ראו, re'u, אם כמחלק מת, im k'mechaleik meit, if he died in
the, you know, at the end, and he meaning after having the
process was a process of dividing. It was clear he was saying
this to this person, this to this person, this to that person,
and then he died. Okay, so in that case that's כל נכסיו.
kol nechasav, It was כל נכסיו kol nechasav but it took time.
It was a process. But they're all part of the same process
of dividing up all of your wealth, all of your property.
אם כמחלק, im k'mechaleik, once again I don't know what's happening, I'm
putting parentheses in the wrong place. אם כמחלק, im k'mechaleik, if he
did it as
distributing all the property, then מת קנו כולם. meit kanu kulam. If
he dies, they all get it, okay, because that's a מתנת שכיב
מרע. matnat shchiv meira עמד, amad, if he gets better, חוזר בכולן.
chozer b'chulan. It all gets reversed. It was all the gifting of
all of his property, it was one process of gifting all of
his property. Okay, that's if it was מחלק. mechaleik. It was seen
as one process of distributing all the property. אם בנימלך, im b'nimlach,
if however he's reconsidering. What he basically does is he says ראובן
Reuven I want to give my house. And that's it! That's what
I'm doing. I'm giving ראובן Reuven my house. And then tomorrow he
says, you know what, I want שמעון Shimon to get my car.
Okay, so then, do we see that as one long process that's
just taking him a long time to distribute everything? Or do we
say no, when he gave ראובן Reuven the house, he was planning
on not giving any of the rest of his property away. He
was planning on having his kids inherit the rest. And then the
next day when he said שמעון Shimon gets my car only then
he started distributing the rest, right? That was a new thing. What
would be the נפקא מינה? nafkaminah? When ראובן Reuven got the car,
was he getting it as a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv meira
or was he getting it as a normal קנין? kinyan. Right, you
see the difference? If we don't look at it as one process
and he just wanted to give ראובן Reuven the car at that
moment, that's not
כל נכסיו.
kol nechasav It's not כל נכסיו.
kol nechasav. Okay, so that's the point. אם בנימלך, im b'nimlach, if
he did it by reconsidering and then adding on to his distributions,
but when he was first doing it it looked like he had
stopped.
Okay, מת קנו כולם. meit kanu kulam. Now it's still true, if
he dies it's all valid. Okay, as long as he did a
קנין kinyan. and it might be in the מצוה mitzvah category. But
as long as he did a קנין, kinyan. and all this we're
assuming he's doing a קנין, kinyan okay so it's a קנין kinyan.
we're assuming, then fine, then everybody's going to get it. Why not?
He still did it with a קנין. kinyan. But here's the difference.
עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. If he gets better, then it
does not get reversed because everything was a legitimate קנין. It wasn't
כל נכסיו, kol nechasav. it was מקצת miktzat. נכסיו. אלא באחרון, ela
b'acharon, the only thing that gets reversed is the last guy he
gave it to, right? Because if every day he's adding somebody else
to the list, right? So ראובן Reuven gets this and that's it.
And tomorrow he says, you know what, שמעון Shimon gets that and
that's it. Okay and then by the time he finally gets to
like בנימין, Binyamin, by בנימין Binyamin got the final last piece of
property that he owned. So בנימין Binyamin was כל נכסיו, kol nechasav.
right? So the בנימין Binyamin was the one that עמד חוזר. amad
chozer, בנימין Binyamin got all that was left of his property.
כל נכסיו kol nechasav, or just a מתנת שכיב מרע?
matnat shchiv meira. Well no, that's what I mean, meaning because it's
כל נכסיו it's a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat shchiv meira, right? A
מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv meira is only when you're giving away
everything, right? So only when it got to בנימין Binyamin everything else
had been given away. Right, but everybody else he weren't giving away
everything. Okay.
So no, I don't mean literally כל נכסיו. I mean what was
left of his נכסיו was at that moment כל נכסיו. Right? You
got it?
Wait so the guy who gets the last piece, yes, that goes
back.
That goes back if you get better because that was a מתנת
שכיב מרע. Matnat shchiv mera. Because at that moment that was all
that was left of his property. But everybody else, they only got
part of his property. Okay,
because it wasn't seen as one process of distributing it all.
So those were a good קנין, those were a good קנין.
Exactly. Okay, so okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now the גמרא Gemara of course asks the obvious question. How do
you know? What does it
mean אם כמחלק, im k'mechaleik, אם בנימלך? im b'nimlach? There's a lot
of cases where you're not going to know, right? So the גמרא
Gemara says ודילמא עיוני קמיעיין והדר יהיב? v'dilma iyuni k'ma'ayin v'hadar yahiv?
How do you know? So maybe he's like, you know, he's just
taking a long time and he's thinking, thinking about who to give
this to and who to give that to and every day he
comes back and he does another piece. But ultimately it's all part
of one process of distributing everything. And so the גמרא Gemara says
סתמי דשכיב מרע מעיין ברישא והדר יהיב. stamei d'sh'chiv mera ma'ayan b'reisha
v'hadar yahiv. A standard case of שכיב מרע is first he thinks
through everything, you know, and then... And then he starts distributing. I
don't know, I bet there are plenty of שכיב מרעס shchiv meiras
that are not like that, okay, which is not by the way
the same point Charlie you made about the does do they know
the way to legally frame it? Right. This could be somebody who
has no idea of legal framing but is saying before you start
saying how you want it distributed, you've got it all figured out
in your head. I don't know if that's necessarily true. Okay. So,
I mean the distinction makes sense, but how to know when to
apply it is a big question. Okay. אמר רב אחא בר מניומי
Amar Rav Achai bar Minyumi so that was very interesting about whether
it's a process or separate acts and whether you look at everything
as מתנת שכיב מרע Matnat shchiv mera, or only the last thing.
So, אמר רב אחא בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Achai
bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman, שכיב מרע שכתב כל נכסיו לאחרים ועמד
shchiv meira shekatav kol nechasav l'acherim v'amad now we're going to really
radically limit a concept or change a concept. שכיב מרע basically gives
all his property out. He gives his house to this person, his
car to that person, he says everything in my bank account goes
to the third person, as far as we can tell it's all
of his property. ועמד, V'amad, and now he gets better, אינו חוזר,
eino chozer, it remains binding. What? It's כל נכסיו. חיישינן
שמא יש לו נכסים במדינה אחרת. Chashinan shema yesh lo nechasim b'medinah
acheret. Who knows? Maybe he's got some money in some bank account
that we don't know about, you know, in some retirement fund buried
in his paperwork. Well, buried in his paperwork we'd find out about
it. But who knows? Maybe there's a little bit of stuff left
somewhere. Of course, if that's true they're basically saying that we're always
in this
category.
That's it, that's
what which is what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask: then
how does when does this category ever work? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא מתניתין דקתני לא שייר קרקע כל שהוא אימא מתנת בקימת
ela matnitan d'katani lo shiyer karka kol shehu eima matnat b'kayemet and
when you're in this category, it's classic מתנת שכיב מרע Matnat shchiv
mera and עמד חוזר, amad chozer. היכי משכחת? heichi mishkachat? When are
you ever going to have that? So אמר רב חמא באומר כל
נכסיי. Amar Rav Chama b'omer kol nechasai. If somebody says "all my
property" to Reuven, so he says all my property. He's not, you
know, it's not that he says X to this person, Y to
this person, and then we look at him and we say, oh,
that was all his property. No, he explicitly says all my property.
And it doesn't have to mean all to one person, he could
say of my all of my property, ten percent to Reuven, fifteen
percent to Shimon, but he's clearly dealing with the totality of his
property. In that case, that would be in this category. Now רשב"ם
Rashbam also quotes a ר"י ri from רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel which
he doesn't like, but is the following: it could still be the
case of my house to this and my car to that and
my yard to this other person, as long as in the process
he says and this constitutes all of my property. So if he
adds that line, right, he could be concrete about what he's distributing
and saying and this is all the property that I own, then
that becomes a מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnat shchiv mera? So that makes
I like that a lot. Okay, but I don't know why the
רשב"ם Rashbam doesn't like it. He quotes it in the name of
רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, but that allows the שכיב מרע the ability
to have full flexibility to be very concrete and specific, and at
the same time to have the clause that's going to let it
reverse if he gets better, right? So just make sure you write
that line. Okay, but for whatever reason the רשב"ם Rashbam doesn't like
that. Okay, so that's one answer, כל נכסיי, kol nechasai, he says
כל נכסיי. kol nechasai. מר בר רב אשי אמר דמוחזק לן דלית
ליה. Mar bar Rav Ashi amar d'muchzak lan d'leit lei. No, it's
not just as far as we can tell he has no property,
we have a חזקה chazakah that he has no more property. I
don't know how you have a חזקה chazakah of whether somebody has
property or not. People are always hiding away their assets or whatnot.
But anyway, but the effect of this is, and this is an
important question to always ask, like when you see like the גמרא
Gemara doing this type of thing that like severely redefines the parameters
of something, so like I mean to me like it's one thing
that we're going to have a debate about the narrow question of
does it work on פירות without, you know, on דבר שלא בא
לעולם, does it work on הלוואה, halva'ah, that's like just formulating conceptually
right what like the scope of it is. But when you take
something and you say pretty much, you know, everything is going to
fall into this category, the מקצת miktzat not the כל נכסיו, you've
got to ask yourself like what's motivating them to do that? With
the effect is עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. That would be
very strange because if you were to ask me, I would think
that if we believe in the institution of מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnat
shchiv mera. we'd want to put more things into this category, right?
Because this category encourages people to use מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv
mera, because they can know, don't worry, you know, it's like, you
know, rabbis it's always like a very interesting thing, you know, we
do a lot of pastoral training in the, you know, in the
ישיבה, yeshiva, but there's an area in הלכה Halacha where already some
of the pastoral training is like built in, which is the issue
about saying וידוי. viduy. Like already the פוסקים poskim were aware that
if you tried to get a person on their deathbed to say
וידוי, viduy, they think that that means that they're going to die,
right? So therefore they're afraid, right, you know, if I say וידוי
viduy then it's okay for me to die or whatever. So they
even like said in הלכה halacha you have to say to the
person, you know, many people say וידוי viduy and then they get
better and blah blah blah, so it even like has that built
in because you want to encourage the person to say it so
you have to alleviate their fears, right? So anyway, if somebody is
saying like, Wait, I don't want to distribute my property, what if
I get better? Then I'm going to be poor. over. So logically,
you want אומד חוזר Amad chozer to be there, if you want
to encourage people to use this institution. If you're going to say
that pretty much every case except some rare exceptions we're going to
consider to be a מצוה לחלק, Mitzvah l'chalek, to me the effect
of that is to really like limit, you know, trying to limit
use of this מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shchiv mera. Again, according to
רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, it works as long as you use the
right language. So that again makes it more of a technicality. You
just have to use the right language. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Where were we? איבעיא להו, Ibaia lehu, they raised the following question:
חזרה במקצת הוי חזרה בכולא או לא? Chazara b'miktzat havi chazara b'chula
o lo?
So here's what he said. He said, I am giving all of
my property to ראובן. Reuven. That's what he says on day one.
On day two he says, you know what, the car, I'm going
to give the car to שמעון. Shimon. Okay? Now, there's a principle
of דיתיקי מבטלת דיתיקי. Daitiki mevatelet daitiki. If it's a מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnat shchiv mera, the same way if he gets better it's
reversed, any later will—a דיתיקי Daitiki is last will and testament—it's because
it supersedes all earlier wills. Okay? So a דיתיקי, Daitiki, a later
will or a later מתנת שכיב מרע מבטלת דיתיקי mevatelet daitiki annuls
earlier wills. So here's the point. He has the about power to
say, forget everything I said yesterday, here's my new will. But he
didn't say that. All he said was, yesterday he said everything to
ראובן Reuven and today he said, you know what, give the car
to שמעון. Shimon. So there's two ways to read that. Let ראובן
Reuven keep everything he has and the only thing he is retracting
is about the car, the car is not going to go to
ראובן, Reuven, it's going to go to שמעון. Shimon. Or the way
two to read it is,
he's retracting his entire gift yesterday. Tear up my previous will completely.
My car is going to שמעון Shimon and the rest is going
to stay for my kids. Okay? So how do you read that?
So is a חזרה במקצת, Chazara b'miktzat, he's changing one piece, is
that reversing everything yesterday or only reversing that one piece?
And since last means the last will and testament and the most
recent one...
yes, totally. It doesn't mean it's last because he's dead. No. It
means it's the most recent one. Yes. And that's how...
find out something new every day. It's really clear.
Okay. So of course a פנקס pinkas you have ten last wills
of testament because that's why you got to...
I'm glad I'm not the only one in the room though that
was confused about that.
Okay, so איבעיא להו חזרה במקצת הוי חזרה בכולא או לא? Ibaia
lehu chazara b'miktzat havi chazara b'chula o lo? Okay.
So is it retracting everything or just that one piece? Big נפקא
מינה, Nafkā mināh, does ראובן Reuven get everything except the car, does
he get nothing? So תא שמע, Ta shema, coming here.
Here's a ברייתא braita that seems to be exactly this case. כולם
לראשון ובקצתם לשני. Kulam l'rishon u'v'miktzatam l'sheni.
The guy says that ראובן Reuven get everything and presumably afterwards he
says, you know what, let שמעון Shimon get something. Okay, what we
used as the car. שני קנה ראשון לא קנה. Sheni kana rishon
lo kana. ראשון לא קנה. Rishon lo kana. So the second guy
gets the car and ראובן Reuven gets nothing. So that seems to
be a clear answer to our question. It's a חזרה בכולא. Chazara
b'chula. Okay? מאי לאו בשמת? Mai lav beshemat?
Presumably it means he died. Okay? And if he died, therefore his
will, you know, his מתנה matanah is valid. So שמעון Shimon gets
the car, but ראובן Reuven gets nothing. Because for ראובן Reuven it
was a complete retraction. So that answers our question. But the גמרא
Gemara says, לא בשעמד. Lo b'sheamad. So the first answer is, sorry,
I think we have to draw. Okay, so... let's see. Okay, here
he is. So
he
says first here's ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. Okay?
So first he says that ראובן Reuven get everything, here that's everything.
I don't know why that everything is a big mound of stuff.
Okay. And then after he says that he says, oh you know
what, let שמעון Shimon get a little bit, he'll give שמעון Shimon
a tree. Okay? It's easier for me to draw a tree than
a car. That looks like a lollipop. Okay, whatever. Anyway, fine. That's
what he gives שמעון. Shimon. He gives שמעון Shimon one thing. Okay.
So anyway, the הלכה is שמעון Shimon gets it, ראובן Reuven gets
nothing. Which means that it was... okay, this started off as all,
this was number one, and then he said, you know what, let
שמעון Shimon get a tree. So if ראובן Reuven gets nothing, presumably
that means that it was a חזרה בכולא. Chazara b'chula. Okay, that's
what we're assuming, right? That seems to be the case. But the
גמרא Gemara says wait, here could be a... and that would be
he died. He died, his מתנה matanah is fulfilled, this goes to
שמעון Shimon and ראובן Reuven gets zero. But what would be if
he got better? Actually...
he's in bed.
Okay, there he is, he's in bed.
So מאי לאו Mai lav the first אוקימתא בשמת? ukimta beshemat? Yeah.
So the car stands, but everything else is בטל, batel, לראשון L'rishon
doesn't get anything. Right. So that's a proof that it's a מתנת
שכיב מרע?
It is a מתנת שכיב מרע. You know the מתנת שכיב מרע
בכולא, Matnat shchiv mera b'chula, and then it was a חזרה במקצת,
Chazara b'miktzat,
so and
it was a חזרה במקצת Chazara b'miktzat which was a... So how
does this work? Because definitely there's a קנין there. Right, so then
this would just be a קנין.
That's what I'm saying.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It's not a מתנת שכיב מרע, it's a קנין.
Once this is בטל batel and this is only מקצת, miktzat
it's a מתנה, matana,
regular מתנה, matana, regular קנין. Right.
Okay, that's what I wanted to clarify. Got it.
Now,
what would happen though? He looks terrible by the way. I know.
What would happen if he got better, if he was עמד? amad?
So if he was עמד, amad, okay, then would this still be
good? Yes. Yes, because it's just a regular קנין. Exactly. So the
גמרא Gemara is saying is maybe, maybe the case is that actually
ראובן Reuven was, what do you call it, ראובן Reuven it was
not חזרה בכולו. chazara b'kula. ראובן Reuven still has basically all of
the whole thing or whatever, almost all, okay? Now he's got 95%
of all because he 5% was given away. Okay. But you know
why ראובן Reuven gets nothing? ראובן Reuven gets nothing and שמעון Shimon
gets the tree because he was עמד. amad.
If he was עמד amad and he got better, okay,
then
now I'm getting. Now you're saying one minute, if he was עמד
amad then what? None of them should get anything. Why shouldn't שמעון?
Shimon?
Because
that's מתנת שכיב מרע.
No, עמד אינו חוזר amad eino chozer when it's the מקצת.
miktzat, Can you do מקצת miktzat and include a חזרה? chazara? Well,
the question is, did he separate the כולו kula amongst others?
Well, your point is, is that if that's true, then this is
make up your mind. If when he gives a little bit this
retains it's a מחלק מחמת mechaleik meichamat
then for everybody it's כולו. kula. Right. And if we look at
them as separate, then for both of them it's like מקצת miktzat.
or whatever. Right. That's the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that.
So that's you're correct. The גמרא's Gemara going to reject this answer.
But right now the גמרא Gemara thinks, it's going to reject it
exactly for what you like what you said, the גמרא thinks that
we could have a case to explain it. No, he retains 95%.
For him it's still a מתנת שכיב מרע, עמד amad. חוזר. chozer
But for שמעון Shimon it's במקצת b'miktzat and עמד אינו חוזר. amad
eino chozer. Which is crazy, because if שמעון Shimon it should certainly
be בכולו. b'kula. By the time you get to שמעון Shimon that's
the only thing left of the מתנה. matana. Okay. So the גמרא's
going to reject that reason but let's go with it for now.
Okay. So the גמרא says like this.
But first it thinks it's a good rule. גמרא says like this.
אי אמרת... Ei amart... so the גמרא says like this. מאי לאו
בשעמד הכי נמי מסתברא. Mai lav beshe'amad hachi nami mistavra. That makes
sense. דקתני סיפא, Dekatani seifa, the end of this ברייתא braita says,
מקצתן לראשון וכולן לשני. miktzatan lerishon vechulan lashaini. Let's say it was
a different version. Okay, let's say the version was, the first he
gave a little bit to ראובן, Reuven, first he gave a tree
to ראובן. Reuven. That's מקצתו... miktzato... I'm making it into a tree,
it's so bizarre. They look like they look like keyholes or something.
Anyway, okay, whatever. Okay, first he gives my artistic skills have gone
down the tubes. Okay. Now let's say he says מקצתן לראשון miktzatan
lerishon and then וכולן לשני. vechulan lashaini. And then he says the
next day he said I'm giving it all to, I'm giving it
all to whatever. Later he said I'm giving all to שמעון. Shimon.
Here's my big pile of money, I'm giving it to שמעון. Shimon.
Okay, giving it all to שמעון. Shimon. Once the קנין is given
and properties given over, how can you retract? Because a שכיב מרע
can, oh, because if this is a קנין במקצת, kinyan b'miktzat, right,
if this is a קנין במקצת, kinyan b'miktzat, he can't retract that,
so then this would be everything that's left. So let's see what
the הלכה is. Okay.
Where were we? Okay. מקצתן לראשון וכולן לשני ראשון קנה שני לא
קנה. miktzatan lerishon vechulan lashaini rishon kana shaini lo kana. So
as you correctly said, okay, this works because this is מקצת, miktzat,
right, that's
a מתנה, matana, standard קנין. Right, that's a standard קנין. So that's
going to remain valid, if he gets better or not better. This
is everything that's left, so this is כולו. kula. Right, this is,
and it can, as I said, even if he wanted to retract
this little bit he couldn't, that was already מקצת miktzat? and binding.
And this is שכיב מרע, okay. Okay, so this works and this
doesn't work. Now what's the scenario? Is the scenario that he got
better or didn't get better?
It has to be that he got better.
Got better. If he didn't get better then this would still work.
Okay, so the
גמרא says... אי אמרת Ei amart that
כולו kula could also be considered a מקצת. miktzat.
Well, it's everything that's left.
But that's also, no, that's כולו. kula. That's everything that was left.
Oh, okay.
You don't, you don't look at it from when, right, this is
right, at when it becomes the new כולו. kula. Exactly. Okay, so,
אי אמרת בשלמא בשעמד ומשום הכי
לא קנה משום הכי שני לא קנה.
Ei amart bishlama beshe'amad umishum hachi lo
kana mishum hachi shaini lo kana. If he got better I guess
why this became voided. Okay. אלא אי אמרת בשמת יקנו שניהם. Ela
ei amart beshemet yiknu sheneihem. So let them both work. So you've
proven your point that this case here has to be עמד. amad
Okay. And that's why this gets negated, right, and this gets negated
and this remains good. Okay. But how does עמד amad still solve
this issue if it's a חזרה בכולו? chazara b'kula? If it's a,
I mean if it's a חזרה במקצת. chazara b'miktzat. If it's a
חזרה במקצת chazara b'miktzat and עמד Amad. retracts this, then it should
also like retract that, right? So it still doesn't explain why this
remains good and that doesn't, which is now what the גמרא is
going to say. You've proven that the second case is a case
of עמד. Amad. Case of the גמרא is going to say like
this. אמר ליה רב יימר לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Yeimar le-Rav
Ashi, דילמא לעולם בעמד. dilma le'olam be-Amad.
Fine,
let the ברייתא Baraita be talking about עמד. Amad, אי אמרת בשלמא
חזרה במקצת הוי חזרה בכולה, Ei amarta bishlama chazara bimiktzat havi chazara
bekulo,
so if when you did the tree that negated this, so then
I get it, היינו דשני ניחא ליה. hainu de-sheni nicha lei. So
this guy keeps it because this becomes now a קניין במקצת kinyan
bimiktzat because it retracted all of this. That was a קניין במקצת.
kinyan bimiktzat. So even though it's עמד, Amad keeps this. Okay, and
he doesn't get anything because it completely retracted. Okay.
Where are we? ניחא ליה. Nicha lei. אלא אי אמרת חזרה במקצת
לא הוי חזרה בכולה, Ela ei amarta chazara bimiktzat lo havi chazara
bekulo, but if it was not a complete retraction and he kept
ninety-five percent and he kept his five percent, okay, so where are
we? לא הוי חזרה בכולה. lo havi chazara bekulo.
הוי ליה כמחלק. Havi lei kemichalek. So fine, so this is then,
so then it's ninety-five to him, five percent to him. So for
everybody it should be כולו. kulo. Okay. ולחד מינייהו לא תיתני. U-lekchad
mineihu lo titni.
It should have worked for either of them. All right. So I
don't get it, he says. If this is not going to be
a retraction to this, then if עמד Amad אינו חוזר eino chozer
here because it's מקצת, right? Then why don't you sort of say
this is מקצת? But anyway, neither of them should be מופסד. mufsad.
If you're just retracting and shifting five percent of the כולו. kulo.
I gave כולו kulo to him. Now I'm shifting five percent to
him. That's a clear case of מחלק. michalek. So עמד Amad should
be חוזר for them all. So אלא, ela, you know what? הלכתא,
hilcheta, you're right. Your original read of this ברייתא Baraita was correct.
והלכתא חזרה במקצת הוי חזרה בכולה. Ve-hilcheta chazara bimiktzat havi chazara bekulo.
Yes,
when you reverse it for a little bit, it negated that completely.
It doesn't matter עמד Amad, or not עמד, this gets completely negated.
This shift completely overrides everything else. And I guess there's ways you
could say it. The guy could say on the next day, he's
saying, I am retaining everything I said for ראובן Reuven except for
the issue of the tree or the car, that I'm moving to
שמעון. Shimon. That would work. But if you just said, I'm giving
this tree to שמעון Shimon after you've given everything to ראובן, Reuven,
that completely rejects this. That completely retracts that. Okay.
רישא, Reisha, so this case משכחת לה בין שמת בין שעמד. mishkachat
lah bein shemet bein she-amad. In this case, when he gave after
giving it all, he gave a little thing to שמעון. Shimon. So
whether he dies or doesn't die, right, the ראובן Reuven gift has
completely been voided. Right. Now שמעון Shimon therefore gets מקצת. So שמעון's
Shimon gift is going to be good whether he gets better or
not gets better. Either way, this is a good gift. Okay. סיפא,
Seifa, the second case, okay, where this doesn't work and this does.
So how could this not work? This was כולו. kulo. The only
way the second part couldn't work is if he got better. לא
משכחת לה אלא כשעמד. Lo mishkachat lah ela kish-amad. Would only work
in a case where he got better. If he didn't get better,
it would all be distributed. If he died, it would all be
distributed. If he got better, the second part which was the כולו,
kulo, the new כולו, kulo, that would no longer be valid. Okay.
Phew. We got through that. יישר כח. Yasher koach.
Pictures help.